<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>debug on A Random Walk</title>
    <link>https://rrampage.github.io/tags/debug/</link>
    <description>Recent content in debug on A Random Walk</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rrampage.github.io/tags/debug/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cargo refused to build my project - A Rust debugging story!</title>
      <link>https://rrampage.github.io/2018/05/09/cargo-refused-to-build-my-project-a-rust-debugging-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rrampage.github.io/2018/05/09/cargo-refused-to-build-my-project-a-rust-debugging-story/</guid>
      <description>An afternoon of debugging!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>Today, I resumed a <code>rust</code> project of mine after a long time. In order to check my last working code, I ran <code>cargo run</code>. But it refused to run with error message:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>....&#34;-Wl,-Bdynamic&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;dl&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;rt&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;pthread&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;pthread&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;gcc_s&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;c&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;m&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;rt&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;pthread&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;util&#34; &#34;-l&#34; &#34;util&#34;
= note: /usr/bin/ld: cannot find Scrt1.o: No such file or directory
          collect2: error: ld returned 1 exit status
</code></pre><h3 id="linker-issues">Linker Issues!</h3>
<p><code>ld</code> is used to link libraries. So, the error was not in the code but in the linking phase. I googled the error and the solution was to have <code>build-essential</code> package installed. But the package was already installed on my machine (it is one of the first packages I install on any development machine).</p>
<p>Some more googling revealed that <code>cargo</code> uses the system <code>cc</code> linker to link to the C runtime. Running <code>which cc</code> gave me <code>$HOME/anaconda3/bin/cc</code>. This <code>cc</code> is part of my Anaconda root environment. (Anaconda is a package manager for scientific computing packages. It is a convenient way for installing multiple versions of packages in different environments).</p>
<p>On Linux, the linker knows where to find the required libraries using the shared library cache. I ran <code>ldconfig -v</code> to refresh it and then try again. Same error!</p>
<p>It is possible to explicitly list directories to include using <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> environment variable. I tried setting the <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> to point to the required directory and then run cargo as <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH=DIR cargo build -v</code>. But it gave the same error.</p>
<p>I thought that <code>cargo</code> must be setting the linker value somewhere, so instead let me try directly compiling with <code>rustc</code>. Even that gave the same error. With this, I eliminated the possibility of some environment variable only affecting <code>cargo</code>.</p>
<h3 id="more-googling">More googling!</h3>
<p>Further searching for the error with &ldquo;rust&rdquo; added showed me results of people having trouble cross-compiling. From this, I learned that cargo has different targets i.e different instruction sets (e,g x86-64, arm, x86, mips), different OSs (e.g linux, windows, freebsd) and different C runtimes (e.g glibc, musl, msvc). The Rust documentation on cargo mentioned that this is called a target triple. The <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/cargo/reference/"><strong>Cargo book</strong></a> mentioned that you can direct cargo to explicitly use a particular linker using RUSTFLAGS environment variable.</p>
<p>Since I am only building for my machine, I had to find out the exact value of the target. Rust gives an exhaustive list of all supported targets by running <code>rustc --print target-list</code>. My target was <code>x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu</code>.</p>
<p>It is possible to pass a linker to <code>cargo</code> explicitly as <code>RUSTFLAGS=&quot;-C linker=x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu&quot; cargo build -v</code>. It worked!</p>
<h3 id="all-time-fix">All-time fix!</h3>
<p>I do not want to do this every time I run <code>cargo</code>. The Cargo book says that cargo uses a global config file in <code>$HOME/.cargo/config</code>.</p>
<p>I added the following to the file:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-toml" data-lang="toml"><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="c"># Specify which linker to use for this target</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">target</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="nx">linker</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">&#34;x86_64-linux-gnu-gcc&#34;</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Now, <code>cargo build</code> works without issues.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disk Space Debugging Checklist</title>
      <link>https://rrampage.github.io/2018/05/04/disk-space-debugging-checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rrampage.github.io/2018/05/04/disk-space-debugging-checklist/</guid>
      <description>Checklist for debugging disk issues on Linux servers</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many times, smoothly running processes stop working mysteriously. You open the logs and see what is happening, only to find that even the logs have stopped updating. But the process itself is running. You SSH to the server and type cd TAB. Bash weeps &ldquo;Unable to create temporary file&rdquo;. The machine is out of disk space&hellip;</p>
<p>Here is a checklist to make disk space debugging easier, using standard Linux utilities so you can get started without having to install anything extra:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><code>df -h</code></strong> command gives you an overview in a readable format about the number of disks mounted and their total and available capacities.</li>
<li>To get an idea of which folders/directories are eating up the maximum space, try out <strong><code>du -ch / | sort -h | tail -n 30</code></strong>. This gives you the 30 most space consuming directories. If you already know which directories generate maximum disk output e.g logs and temp files, you can replace the &lsquo;/&rsquo; with your directory (DIR) and run the command as <strong><code>du -ch DIR | sort -h | tail -n 30</code></strong></li>
<li>Now that we have identified the directories with maximum space consumed, we may need to delete some files and get our process going again. The <strong><code>rm</code></strong> command is your friend here. You can delete old logs and temporary files to free up space.</li>
<li>Many times, the culprit is a single large file which is already in use by a program e.g <code>catalina.out</code> by Apache Tomcat. If you want to free up space without shutting down the process, the <strong><code>truncate</code></strong> command will help you out. Example: <strong><code>truncate -s0 BIG_LOG.log</code></strong>. This will truncate the file to 0 bytes and still allow the other process to use it without issues (standard Unix permissions apply)</li>
<li>Sometimes, you delete files and still, the space does not seem to be recovered. This can be because some process is still holding on to the file descriptor of the deleted file. Once these processes are stopped, the space will be recovered. The <strong><code>lsof</code></strong> command will help you out here. It stands for <em>list open files</em>. You can find out which processes are using deleted files as follows: <code>lsof | grep deleted | grep OLD_FILENAME</code>. The lsof command gives you the process name and the process id so you can run <code>kill</code> on the process. If you do not know the name of the deleted file, you can still run <code>lsof | grep deleted</code> and see the output to check for any familiar file / process.</li>
</ol>
<p>Finally, keep in mind that disk space is one of the metrics you should monitor on your server. This checklist must be used in a pinch. If you find yourself constantly having disk space issues, the solution is to set up periodic deletion/rotation of old log files, alerts when the disk space reaches a particular threshold or to increase the disk size if your processes require a lot of disk space e.g Kafka, MySQL and other databases.</p>
<p>Let me know if there are some other tools I am missing out on and your experiences dealing with disk space issues!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
